Guide to the Elizabeth Spires Papers, 1971-2013
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Elizabeth Spires Papers
1971-2013
Spires, Elizabeth
4.2 cubic feet (11 boxes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
This collection consists of correspondence, audiovisual materials, manuscripts, and printed materials documenting the career of poet Elizabeth Spires.
Biographical Note
Elizabeth Spires graduated from Vassar College in 1974. A noted poet, Spires has published eight collections of poems, including Globe (1981), Swan's Island (1997), and A Memory of the Future (2018). In addition, she has written two children's books, The Mouse of Amherst (2001) and I Heard God Talking to Me: William Edmonton and His Stone Carvings (2009), and edited The Instant of Knowing: Lectures, Criticism and Occasional Prose, by Josephine Jacobson (1997). As of 2025, Spires is professor of English and co-director of Kratz Center for Creative Writing at Goucher College, where she holds a Chair for Distinguished Achievement.
Scope and Content Note
This collection consists of correspondence, audiovisual materials, manuscripts, and printed materials documenting the career of poet Elizabeth Spires. Of particular note are the audio cassettes on which are recorded Spires's 1978 interview with poet Elizabeth Bishop (Vassar Class of 1934), a transcription of which later appeared in The Paris Review (no. 80 [1981]).
Access
This collection is open for research according to the regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library without any additional restrictions.
Related Material
The William Gifford Papers contains letters from Elizabeth Spires to William Gifford, with poems written by Spires at Vassar and annotated by Gifford.
Subject Headings
Names:
Bishop, Elizabeth, 1911-1979
Organizations:
Vassar College--Alumni and alumnae
Subjects:
American poetry--20th century; American poetry--21st century.; Poets, American--20th century; Poets, American--21st century; Women poets--United States--20th century; Women poets--United States--21st century
VCL Categories:
Literature and Writing; Vassar College
Encoding Information
Encoded by Mark Seidl, May 2020. Updated, March 2022. Last updated, June 2025.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Elizabeth Spires (VC 1974), 2012-2021. (M2012-008, M2013-008, M2021-008, M2021-009).
Series List
- Series I. Writings, (Box 1-4)
  This series includes undergraduate papers, published and unpublished poems, drafts of poems, lectures, informal talks, and introductions. Also included is Spires's M.A. thesis, "Globe," submitted to Johns Hopkins University in 1979. Drafts include multiple iterations of poems, many with handwritten annotations, arranged by title by Spires.
- Series II. Correspondence, (Box 5-8, 10)
  This series contains letters to and from Spires, the bulk of which encompasses her long correspondence with Vassar College English professor William Gifford. Other correspondents include David Barber, Jill Bialosky, Elizabeth Bishop, Anthony Hecht, Josephine Jacobsen, Judith Kroll, Philip Levine, Howard Moss, John Frederick Nims, Ann Patchett, Melissa Range, Ken Rosen, Megan Sexton, and Richard Wilbur.
- Series III. Clippings, (Box 9-10)
  This series includes clippings of reviews of Spires's publications, as well as book reviews written by Spires.
- Series IV. Photographic Prints, (Box 9)
  The folder in this series contains professional and personal photographs of Spires.
- Series V. Printed Material, (Box 9-10)
  This series contains promotional materials from symposia, readings, and other events in which Spires participated. Also included are uncorrected galleys and offprints of Spires's publications.
- Series VI. Audiovisual Material, (Box 11)
  This series includes VHS, DVD, and audio cassette recordings of conferences, readings, and interviews.
Container List
- Series I. WRITINGS
  - Academic papers
    - M.A. Thesis, Globe, Poems submitted to Johns Hopkins University, 1979 (Folder 1.1)
    - Undergraduate papers, Vassar, Princeton, 1970-1974 (Folders 1.2-1.4)
    - Unpublished MS, Tree of Heaven, Sleepy Head, Red and Green Forever, undated (Folder 1.5)
  - Published/Unpublished poems
    - Miscellaneous poems, published/unpublished, 1990-2013 (Folder 1.6)
    - Miscellaneous poems, published, including student submissions to Spires, 1986-1987 (Folder 1.7)
    - Miscellaneous poetry by E.S., 1972-1977 (Folder 1.8)
    - Miscellaneous poems with notations, 1977-1992 (Folders 1.9-1.12)
    - Poetry set to music, Nancy Gunn, Gary Friedman, William Bradbury, 1994-1995 (Folder 1.13)
    - Vassar College submissions, with comments from Judith Kroll, William Gifford, 1972-1974 (Folders 1.14-1.17)
  - Poems, drafts
    - A Life, undated (Folder 2.1)
    - The Amiable Child, undated (Folder 2.2)
    - Anamnesis (When We Meet Again), undated (Folder 2.3)
    - Annonciade, undated (Folder 2.4)
    - Badger Disguised as a Monk, undated (Folder 2.5)
    - The Beds, undated (Folder 2.6)
    - The Bells, undated (Folder 2.7)
    - Black Fairytale, undated (Folder 2.8)
    - The Celestial, undated (Folder 2.9)
    - Cemetery Reef, undated (Folder 2.10)
    - Coelacanth, undated (Folder 2.11)
    - The Comb in the Mirror, undated (Folder 2.12)
    - Curling Willow, undated (Folder 2.13)
    - Elegy for Alex, undated (Folder 2.14)
    - Essential Snail, undated (Folder 2.15)
    - Fabergé’s Egg, undated (Folder 2.16)
    - The First Day, undated (Folder 2.17)
    - Ghazal, undated (Folder 2.18)
    - Glass Bottomed Boat, undated (Folder 2.19)
    - Island Graveyard, undated (Folder 2.20)
    - Riddle, undated (Folder 2.21)
    - Josephine, undated (Folder 2.22)
    - Leaf Memory, undated (Folder 2.23)
    - Life of I, undated (Folder 2.24)
    - The Little Boys, undated (Folder 2.25)
    - Love Presumes, undated (Folder 2.26)
    - A Memory of the Future, undated (Folder 2.27)
    - Moment Vanishing, Côte d'Azur, undated (Folder 2.28)
    - Netsuke, undated (Folder 3.1)
    - Now the Green Blade Rises, undated (Folder 3.2)
    - Picture of a Soul, undated (Folder 3.3)
    - Pome, undated (Folder 3.4)
    - Primos, undated (Folder 3.5)
    - Profil Perdu, undated (Folder 3.6)
    - The Red Boomerang, undated (Folder 3.7)
    - The Rehearsal, undated (Folder 3.8)
    - Remembering Poughkeepsie, undated (Folder 3.9)
    - Rosa Tacchini, undated (Folder 3.10)
    - The Shrine, undated (Folder 3.11)
    - A Small Voice Asks Some Large Questions, undated (Folder 3.12)
    - Snow, The Novel, undated (Folder 3.13)
    - Soliloquy on Clouds, undated (Folder 3.14)
    - The Sound of the Sea at the Shore; Like Water, undated (Folder 3.15)
    - Starry Night, undated (Folder 3.16)
    - Story of a Soul; Brown Bird, undated (Folder 3.17)
    - Sunday Afternoon at Fulham Palace, undated (Folder 3.18)
    - Sunday Morning at the Carmelite Monastery; Zazen, undated (Folder 3.19)
    - Thanksgiving Night, undated (Folder 3.20)
    - They Drive Through Childhood in Tiny Cars, undated (Folder 3.21)
    - The Time Traveler, undated (Folder 3.22)
    - To a Fog Spirit, undated (Folder 3.23)
    - A Tomb; Half Lit, undated (Folder 3.24)
    - Translation of My Life, undated (Folder 3.25)
    - Troubadour at a Fork in the Road, undated (Folder 3.26)
    - Two Chairs on a Hillside, undated (Folder 3.27)
    - Unsung Song, undated (Folder 4.1)
    - Victoriana, undated (Folder 4.2)
    - The Walk, undated (Folder 4.3)
    - Worldling, Now the Green Blade Rises, undated (Folders 4.4-4.10)
    - You have Flown to the Dangerous Country, undated (Folder 4.11)
  - Talks
    - Anthony Hecht Felt and Mastered Pain, 2000 Apr (Folder 4.12)
    - On Elizabeth Bishop, Alice Tully Hall, 1997 Oct (Folder 4.13)
    - Emily Dickinson, a Mouse, and Me, undated (Folder 4.14)
    - Emily Dickinson Birthday, Folger Shakespeare Library, undated (Folder 4.15)
    - Encounters with Zen and What I've Learned from Japanese Art, Goucher College, undated (Folder 4.16)
    - George Herbert, Gerard Manley Hopkins, Elizabeth Bishop Poetry, Columbia University, 2004 Sep (Folder 4.17)
    - Josephine Jacobsen, 2017 (Folder 4.18)
    - Reading My Way Through Childhood, undated (Folder 4.19)
    - The Triggering Voice, Gettysburg College, 2000 Sep (Folder 4.20)
    - Visual Emotion, Imaginary Possession, Poetry of Marianne Moore, 1987 Feb (Folder 4.21)
    - The Writer's Changing Voice, Sicily, Washington, D.C., undated (Folder 4.22)
    - The Writing Process, Going Back to the Source, undated (Folder 4.23)
- Series II. CORRESPONDENCE
  - Acceptance letters of published work in Mademoiselle, Poetry, Antaeus, Miscellany, VA Quarterly Review, undated (Folder 5.1)
  - Barber, David, The Atlantic Monthly, following publication of "The Wave Maker,", undated (Folder 5.2)
  - Bialosky, Jill, Spires's poetry editor, Norton, 2010, 2013 (Folder 5.3)
  - Cole, Henri, 1989-1994 (Folder 5.4)
  - Comstock, Rolland, 1991 Mar (Folder 5.5)
  - Ford, Harry, Atheneum Publishers, Rejection of The Daughter of Time, undated (Folder 5.6)
  - Jacobsen, Josephine, 1990-2002 (Folders 5.7-5.8)
  - Hecht, Anthony, 2000 Feb (Folder 5.9)
  - Kroll, Judith, 1973-1974 (Folder 10.5)
  - Kurtenbach, Elaine, Wesleyan University Press, approval of publication of Globe, undated (Folder 5.10)
  - Levine, Phil, 1998 Feb (Folder 5.11)
  - Meredith, William, CT College, publication of Crazy Quilt and Storyville Portrait, 1982 May (Folder 5.12)
  - Moss, New Yorker, first acceptance of published work, Widow's Walk, 1976 (Folder 5.13)
  - Moss, Howard, submission of Waving Goodbye, 1982 Sep (Folder 5.14)
  - Nims, John, 1992 Feb (Folder 5.15)
  - Patchett, Ann, 2010 Nov (Folder 5.16)
  - Pelizzon, Penelope, 2012 Mar (Folder 5.17)
  - Range, Melissa, 2005, 2006 (Folder 5.18)
  - Rosen, Kenneth, 2011 May (Folder 5.19)
  - Sexton, Megan, 2011 Feb (Folder 5.20)
  - Snodgrass, W.D., 1978-2000 (Folders 5.21-5.23)
  - Strand, Mark, 1974-1977 (Folder 5.24)
  - Teller, Walter, 1978 May (Folder 5.25)
  - Warren, Rosanna, 2009-2013 (Folder 5.26)
  - White House (Laura Bush) Poetry Symposium invite and subsequent cancellation, email from Russell Banks, 2003 Jan-Feb (Folder 5.27)
  - Weaver, William, re Witter Bynner Poetry Prize, American Academy of Arts and Letters, 1998 Mar (Folder 5.28)
  - Wilbur, Richard, 1997 May (Folder 5.29)
  - to Gifford, William, 1976-2008 (Folders 6.1-6.21)
  - to Gifford, William, 1976-2008 (Folders 7.1-7.9)
  - to Gifford, William (re: Elizabeth Bishop research), 1982-1994 (Folders 7.10-7.12)
  - from Gifford, William, 1973-2015 (Folder 8.1-8.15)
  - from Bishop, Elizabeth, 1966-1979 (Folder 8.16-8.23)
    Letters from Bishop to Vassar administrators, including William Gifford, W.K. Rose, regarding Bishops' invitation to be Vassar's Phi Beta Kappa poet.
- Series III. CLIPPINGS
  - A Memory of the Future, reviews, 2018 (Folder 9.1)
  - Annonciade, reviews, 1989-1993 (Folder 9.2)
  - I Am Arachne, reviews, 2001 (Folder 9.3)
  - I Heard God Talking to Me, reviews, 2001 (Folder 9.4)
  - Globe, reviews, 1981-1985 (Folder 9.5)
  - Kate's Light, reviews, 2021 (Folder 9.6)
  - The Mouse of Amherst, reviews, 1999 (Folder 9.7)
  - Now the Green Blade Rises, reviews, 2002 (Folder 9.8)
  - With One White; Ridge Road, reviews, 1995-1999 (Folder 9.10)
  - Worldling, reviews, 1995-1996 (Folder 9.11)
  - Book reviews written by E. Spires, American Poetry Review, New Criterion, Chicago Tribune, New York Times, 1987-2012 (Folder 9.12)
  - Book reviews written by E. Spires, American Poetry Review, New Criterion, Chicago Tribune, New York Times, 1987-2012 (Folders 10.1-10.2)
  - W.D. Snodgrass interview by E. Spires, American Poetry Review, 1990 (Folder 10.3)
- Series IV. PHOTOGRAPHIC PRINTS
  - Personal and professional photographs of Elizabeth Spires, 1979-1985 (Folder 9.13)
- Series V. PRINTED MATERIAL
  - Award, Ohioana Book Award, 1999 (Folder 9.14)
  - Bishop, Elizabeth, reprints, interviews, articles, news clippings-collected by William Gifford, 1966-2001 (Folder 10.6)
  - Broadside - "Brown Bird," The Beall Poetry Festival (signed), 2006 (Map Case - Drawer 37)
  - Broadside - "The Celestial," Hatch Showprints, Nashville, TN (29/100), undated (Map Case - Drawer 37)
  - Broadside - Poetry in Motion, New York MTA, 1999 Jan 3 (Map Case - Drawer 37)
  - Ghazal, Poetry for Students, Gale Group Study Guide offprint copy, 2014 (Folder 9.15)
  - Hollins Critic, In the Everlasting Present: the Poetry of Elizabeth Spires, 2002 Apr (Folder 9.16)
  - Events, readings, symposia promotion, 1979-1999 (Folder 9.17)
  - Uncorrected galleys, Annonciade, 1989 (Folder 9.18)
  - Uncorrected galleys, I am Arachne, 2001 (Folder 9.19)
  - Uncorrected galleys, The Mouse of Amherst, 1999 (Folder 9.20)
  - Uncorrected galleys, Swan's Island, 1985 (Folder 9.21)
- Series V. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS
  - Bread Loaf Writers' Conference, Middlebury, VT, 1997 Aug 1; (VHS tape) (Box 11)
  - Easter Sunday 1955 poems read by Elizabeth Spires, 1996 Apr 1; (audio cassette) (Box 11)
  - Gunn and Spires, songs, 1994; (3 audio cassettes) (Box 11)
  - Howard County Poetry and Literature Society, Interviews by E.S. - Donald Hall, 2009 Oct 1; (DVD) (Box 11)
  - Howard County Poetry and Literature Society, Interviews by E.S. - Philip Levine, 1998 Mar 1; (DVD) (Box 11)
  - Howard County Poetry and Literature Society, Josephine Jacobsen Tribute with poets Lucille Clifton, Michael Collier, Elizabeth Spires, 2003; (VHS tape) (Box 11)
  - Howard County Poetry and Literature Society, Michael Collier hosts Elizabeth Spires, 2002 Oct 1; (VHS tape) (Box 11)
  - Intimations of Genius, Key West Literary Seminar, Alice Methfessel, 1993; (2 audio cassettes) (Box 11)
  - Irregular resolutions, 5th Annual New Music Concert, 2009 Oct 1; (CD) (Box 11)
  - NPR, All Things Considered, "On the Island," ready by Elizabeth Spires, 1995 Aug 1; (audio cassette) (Box 11)
  - Omni Author to Author discussion, series host George Garrett, 1990; (VHS tape) (Box 11)
  - The Great Sea, by Gary Friedman, based on a poem by Elizabeth Spires, 2000 Nov 1; (audio cassette) (Box 11)
  - The Influence of Elizabeth Bishop, Key West Literary Seminar, 1993; (4 audio cassettes) (Box 11)
  - Vassar poetry reading by Elizabeth Spires, 1996 Feb 1; (audio cassette) (Box 11)